Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Welcome to the last stop of
Masechet Kiddushin מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, daf peh bet דף פ"ב, daf
peh bet, 82. We pick up on the middle of peh alef
amud bet פ"א עמוד ב' peh alef amud bet about, about, I
don't even know, exactly in the middle
of the wide lines with the two dots, mityached adam im imo
מתייחד אדם עם אמו. mityached adam im imo. Okay, so it's about,
I don't know, about two-fifths of the way down, 20-25 lines down.
Mityached adam im imo מתייחד אדם עם אמו, mityached adam im imo,
middle of the line, two dots. A man can be in yichud
ייחוד yichud together with his mother and a father with his daughter.
Okay, and the Mishnah משנה Mishnah continues to say it's a quote
from Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, they can even sleep together in the same
bed, even without, even without pajamas on, nightclothes on, until, until it
says they become older. It doesn't exactly tell you what the age
of older is. Okay, so that's a parent with a child. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara looks at other relations. Let's take a look
or other possibilities. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel amar Rav אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel amar Rav.
Amar Rav Assi אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, Rav Yehuda רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the name of Rav Assi רב אסי,
Rav Assi, mityached adam im achoto מתייחד אדם עם אחותו, mityached adam
im achoto, a person, and person obviously we're talking about the man's
perspective, can even be in yichud ייחוד yichud together with his sister,
and this is presumably his adult sister and so on, even though
of course acknowledging that the major category of arayot עריות arayot in
the Torah תורה Torah is incest, right? And, you know, but maybe
this is a sense that even though it's a major category of
arayot עריות, arayot, there's not a strong yetzer hara יצר הרע yetzer
hara for it, although again who knows, as Freud says, you don't
need taboos about something that nobody is doing. So on the other
or maybe it's just an acknowledgment of reality, like, you know, we
have to let people grow up together in the same household. What
does it mean when whenever the parents leave all of a sudden,
the brothers and sisters can't stay at home or whatever? So anyway,
so one or the other, the Gemara גמרא Gemara understands either because
of a concern of a less of a concern of sexual temptation
or because of realities, that according to this position of Rav Assi
רב אסי, Rav Assi, a man can be have yichud ייחוד yichud
together with his sister. Veddar im imo ve'im bito ודר עם אמו
ועם בתו, veddar im imo ve'im bito, and but by the mother
or daughter, meaning a parental relationship, mother and son, father and daughter,
we are even more lenient and we don't just allow yichud ייחוד,
yichud, we allow them to live, actually live together permanently. Okay, so
meaning now I don't know exactly what that means. Obviously, you're also
living with your sister in the same house, right? But maybe again,
I'm not exactly sure what the line would be. When you grow
up and you're your own baal habayit בעל הבית, baal habayit, you
can't have your sister live with you. You know, what exactly is
the line between living with your mother and not living with your
sister? When you're growing up in the same house with your sister,
you're living with your sister. But anyway, clearly Shmuel's always been very
strict. Well, right, but your bar mitzvah בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, I
don't know. Sometimes maybe that's the Gemara's גמרא Gemara assumption that once
you're bar mitzvah בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, you're moving out of the
house. I don't know. Anyway, until they're married, right? Right. Okay, we
can figure it out, but there's some difference here. All right. Now
that was the position of Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi רב יהודה
אמר רב אסי. Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi. Ki amar kamay d'Shmuel
כי אמר קמיה דשמואל, Ki amar kamay d'Shmuel, when he, when I
said it in front of Shmuel שמואל, Shmuel, amar asur l'hityached im
kol arayot shebaTorah אמר אסור להתייחד עם כל עריות שבתורה. amar asur
l'hityached im kol arayot shebaTorah. No, chas veshalom חס ושלום, chas veshalom,
you can't have yichud ייחוד yichud with any of the relations in
the Torah תורה. Torah. Presumably not only sister, it sounds like he's
even including mother and daughter, right? I don't know how the heck
he what you're supposed to do in that case. I guess as
soon as the father leaves to work, the son has to go
out of the house with the father. Like, I don't know exactly
how this is supposed to work.
Shmuel's always been very strict.
Yeah, Shmuel שמואל Shmuel has been very strict and he's going to
continue to be very strict. Ve'afilu im behemah ואפילו עם בהמה, ve'afilu
im behemah, and not only that, you can't even be in yichud
ייחוד yichud together with a beast, an animal, any possible arayot עריות,
arayot, no pets, no whatever, no farm animals, none. Now let's see
if Shmuel's שמואל Shmuel statement really works. Mityached adam im imo ve'im
bito מתייחד אדם עם אמו ועם בתו, mityached adam im imo ve'im
bito, this is the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. You can have yichud ייחוד
yichud with your mother and daughter. Veyashen imahem b'kiruv basar וישן עמהם
בקירוב בשר, veyashen imahem b'kiruv basar, and you can sleep with them
actually, you know, skin to skin. So obviously this is talking while
they're still small. Vetyuvta deShmuel ותיובתא דשמואל, vetyuvta deShmuel, a clear contradiction
of Shmuel שמואל. Shmuel. Amar lach Shmuel אמר לך שמואל, Amar lach
Shmuel, Shmuel שמואל Shmuel would say to you, l'taameich chada tanya לטעמך
חדא תניא? l'taameich chada tanya? According to your reason, is that the
only thing that's taught? Ke'idach tanya כאידך תניא, ke'idach tanya, as it
was taught in a Baraita ברייתא, Baraita, achoto vechamoto veshar kol arayot
shebaTorah ein mityached imahem ella b'edim אחותו וחמותו ושאר כל עריות שבתורה
אין מתייחד עמהם אלא בעדים. achoto vechamoto veshar kol arayot shebaTorah ein
mityached imahem ella b'edim. A Baraita ברייתא Baraita says that sister and
mother-in-law and any other of the arayot עריות, arayot, you cannot have
yichud ייחוד yichud unless there are witnesses present, which means that you
can't have yichud ייחוד. yichud. Okay, so b'edim in, shelo b'edim lo
בעדים אין שלא בעדים לא, b'edim in, shelo b'edim lo, only with
witnesses, not without witnesses. So that goes against, meaning that's consistent with
the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, because the Mishnah משנה Mishnah only gave the
exception of mother and daughter, okay? But and the Baraita ברייתא Baraita
is consistent with that and says yes, but sisters and other relatives
are off. That's all very consistent within the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. But
Shmuel שמואל Shmuel says, but it goes against Rav Assi רב אסי,
Rav Assi, because Rav Assi רב אסי Rav Assi said it's okay
with the sister. So you're telling me I say not okay with
the sister and not okay even with mother or daughter, presumably, that's
against the Mishnah משנה. Mishnah. Well, I'll tell you, Rav Assi רב
אסי Rav Assi is against the Baraita ברייתא. Baraita. Okay, so better
to be against a Baraita ברייתא Baraita than against a Mishnah משנה.
Mishnah. But anyway, so the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, ela tannai hi
אלא תנאי היא. ela tannai hi. You know what? This is a
whole debate of Tannaim תנאים. Tannaim. You can take a very lenient
opinion like Rav Assi רב אסי, Rav Assi, that even with, you
know, with other relatives it's okay, okay? And then the question is
who's included in other relatives? I mean, he says sister, but, you
know, would it also be mother-in-law, whatever? Anyway, you can be like
Rav Assi רב אסי, Rav Assi, even other relatives is okay. You
can take the Mishnah משנה Mishnah which is a middle position, mother
and, you know, child and father... and parent yes, other relatives no.
That's the משנה, Mishnah, that's with the ברייתא, Beraita, that's the middle
position, or the שמואל Shmuel position which is everything is אסור. Assur.
Okay, now where are we going to see an idea that supports
the שמואל Shmuel position that everything is אסור? Assur? So דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. Beraita. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir,
היזהרו בי מפני בתי, Hizaharu bi mipnei biti, be careful with me
regarding my daughter, meaning he said to the people in his house,
you know, if, don't ever let me be alone with my daughter
like make sure, you know, that there's always somebody else in the
room at the same time. Yep.
אמר רבי טרפון Amar Rabbi Tarfon says רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, היזהרו
בי מפני כלתי, Hizaharu bi mipnei kallati, you know what, I don't
want to be, don't leave me alone in the same room with
my daughter-in-law, make sure there's somebody else in the room. So ליגלג
עליו אותו תלמיד, Ligleg alav oto talmid, a certain student like, well,
you know, was sort of mocking, derisive of this. What, what type
of a יצר הרע Yetzer hara does he have, or what type
of a חומרא Chumra is that he has, he doesn't want to
be alone with his daughter-in-law?
So, so אמר רבי אבהו משום רבי חנינא בן גמליאל, Amar Rabbi
Abbahu mishum Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel, לא היו ימים מועטים, Lo hayu
yamim muatim, it was not many days after that student was mocking
him, עד שנכשל אותו תלמיד בחמותו, Ad shenichshal oto talmid b’chamoto, and
then that student himself wound up having, you know, a sexual transgression,
sinned with his mother-in-law. Okay, once again repeating the theme that people,
you know, cannot, that the יצר הרע Yetzer hara for sex is
very powerful and we sort of ignore it at our own peril.
So, also maybe the idea about, you know, about what's the statement
about כל הפוסל במומו פוסל, Kol haposel bemumo posel, you know? So
you don't want to acknowledge it within yourself and therefore you made
fun of other people. Anyway, okay. So, anyway, but this is now
hitting on that theme which is going to say that like everything
is אסור, Assur, you know, even a daughter. I mean okay, daughter-in-law,
mother-in-law, that's already a little bit removed, right? But even a daughter
according to this, everything is אסור. Assur. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, again, I don't know exactly how you arrange, you know, the
living arrangements especially in a one-room house. But okay, let's keep on
reading.
Okay, where were we? Now אפילו בבהמה, Afilu b’behemah, about שמואל Shmuel
said even with an animal, we're going to see that in the
next משנה, Mishnah, that you know, I mean there actually is a
position like that of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but שמואל Shmuel again
that seems to be very extreme, but שמואל Shmuel is saying that.
Okay, so אביי, Abaye, now we're going to see some אמוראים Amoraim
that follow that concern. אביי מכלי להו מכולי דברא, Abaye machlei lehu
mikulei d’vabra, אביי Abaye made sure that when he was out in
the field learning or whatever he was doing, there wouldn't be any
animals within anywhere on the field, like removed them, okay, destroyed them.
Okay, רב ששת מעבר להו מצרא, Rav Sheshet maavar lehu mitzara, רב
ששת Rav Sheshet sort of made sure they were on the other
side of the bridge or the other side of the river, okay.
רב חנא מנהרדעא Rav Chana mi-Neharde'a to be a shepherd? You find...
Oh, רב ששת Rav Sheshet was blind, that's also a good point.
Hi yeah, it's a good question, it's a good question. You have
to go out walking your sheep with other shepherds like, I don't
know, okay. I don't know how you're supposed to live in your
home if you're מחמיר machmir about your daughter or your son, I
don't know how you're supposed to be a shepherd, yes?
So just to note like there are other עריות, arayot, namely two
men and like
that's coming up in the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay. רב חנא מנהרדעא
איקלע לבי רב כהנא לפום נהרא, Rav Chana mi-Neharde’a ikla l’vei Rav
Kahana l’Fum Nahara, רב חנא מנהרדעא Rav Chana mi-Neharde'a came to, you
know, drop by to רב כהנא Rav Kahana in this place, Fum
Nahara. חזייה דיתיב וקא גריס, Chazaye d’yativ v’ka garis, he saw that
רב כהנא Rav Kahana was sitting and, you know, learning, וקיימא בהמה
קמיה, V’kaima behemah kameih, and there was an animal right there, could
you imagine? There was a cow right in front of him where
he was sitting and
learning. So אמר ליה לא סבר ליה מר אפילו בבהמה, Amar leh
lo savar leh mar afilu b’behemah, don't you hold, now it's so
funny because you're quoting a statement in the name of שמואל, Shmuel,
but it's sort of being quoted as if it's a תנאי Tannaic
statement, it didn't say don't you hold of what שמואל Shmuel said,
don't you hold of this, you know, it's almost like there's this,
there's this תנאי Tannaic source. Anyway, don't you hold that even with
an animal you shouldn't have ייחוד? Yichud? אמר ליה, Amar leh, again
it's also funny, since when is ייחוד? Yichud? You're out in the
field. If other people can walk by, you know, which is an
interesting question, what does it mean to be secluded, right? You remember
for example the גמרא Gemara before talked about going with the husband
and wife to another city and the two תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei chachamim.
So seclusion is not only like in a, in a room, in
a structure, in a building, right? You can have two people alone
in the forest, that's also ייחוד, Yichud, right? But nevertheless you imagine
a field where people are grazing animals that anybody could walk, you
know, could come by, it's sort of like פתח פתוח לרשות הרבים,
Petach patuach l’reshut harabbim, you know? Like why even define it as
ייחוד, Yichud, yes? And someone did come by. And someone did come
by, exactly. So like it's very strange, right? So this all seems
quite excessive.
Anyway, what did he say back? לאו אדעתאי. Lav adaitai. Oy, I
wasn't thinking. Thank you for pointing that out to me, right? Which
is of course ironic because you were so distracted you weren't thinking
and nevertheless were concerned about it. Now look at תוספות. Tosafot. The
question is how do we פסקן? Pasken? Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says
אביי מכלי להו מכולי דברא, Abaye machlei lehu mikulei d’vabra, we did
a lot of good פסק Psak yesterday, too bad you weren't there.
אביי מכלי, Abaye machlei, we'll make sure we leave all the פסק
Psak for days you're not here. אביי מכלי להו מכולי דברא, Abaye
machlei lehu mikulei d’vabra, נראה דהני אמוראי חומרא בעלמא קא עבדי, Nireh
d’hanei amoraye chumra b’alma ka avdi, they were just being extra stringent.
ואנן קיימא לן כדרבנן דרבי יהודה דאמרי לא נחשדו ישראל לא על
משכב זכור ולא על הבהמה, V’anan kaima lan k’darabbanan d’Rabbi Yehuda d’amri
lo nechshedu Yisrael lo al mishkav zachur v’lo al habehemah, which is
we're going to see the case of two men. בהמה Behemah isn't
a concern. Okay, that's all very. Okay, that's all very nice, these
are just excessive חומרות, chumras, as we said, it's probably not even
a ייחוד yichud scenario. But what it doesn't answer is, and presumably
we're going to פוסקן pasken like the משנה, mishna, that daughter and
son is okay. But what about the other relatives? What about sister?
Right? What's so that, you know, sister or brother, whatever. Those are
questions. What about grandmother? Okay, those are questions. So those are debates
of פוסקים poskim about how we come out with those. Okay. So
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, if you have a real הלכה למעשה halacha
l'maaseh question you can talk to me afterwards. Okay, but that's מחלוקת
הפוסקים. machlokes haposkim. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מתייחד אדם עם שתי יבמות
misyachid adam im shtei yevamot עם שתי... Now, so again, a man
can't be with two women because we're afraid he'll seduce both of
them, or he'll seduce one and the other one will go along
and keep quiet. But if the other, there're two women who hate
one another, then it's okay because if you seduce one, if the
man seduces one of them, the other one is going to tell
everybody about it because she wants to ruin the person's reputation. Okay,
so that makes it more מותר. It's the same way like אשתו
ואמה ishto v'imah and other types of things. So if they hate
one another, then it's okay. Then everybody's going to be what, be
at top watching everybody else's behavior.
Oh, we're going to get to it. שתי יבמות, shtei yevamot, two
sister-in-laws, they hate one another because if one of the husbands dies,
then this one might become a co-wife because of the מצווה mitzvah
of יבום. yibbum. עם שתי צרות, im shtei tzarot, literally two co-wives.
עם אשה וחמותה, im isho v'chamoso, a woman and her mother-in-law. עם
אשה ובת בעלה, im isho u'bat ba'ala, a woman and her stepdaughter.
Okay. עם אשה... okay, now, so that's all because they're going to
report on it and you're not going to be able to to
to get it, you know, to do it, the man won't be
able to seduce one and have the other one keep quiet. Also,
in somebody who you can't keep quiet is עם אשה ותינוקת, a
woman and a young kid. Because as we know, the you can't
do anything in front of the kids or say anything because they'll
just repeat it to anybody, you know, because they're just going to
blab, right? They don't have any discretion. So if there's actually a
young kid, it actually improves the situation of ייחוד yichud because the
kid is going to just say, oh, guess what I saw, you
know? So anyway, okay. שיודעת טעם ביאה sheyoda'at ta'am biah ואין מוסרת
עצמה לביאה. v'ein moseret atzmah l'biah. It has to be somebody that
understands what sex is so that, you know, it'll be something that
they will report on and, you know, and so on. But B,
but it has to be also someone who is not going to
allow themselves to, you know, to... let's look at רש"י, Rashi, let's
look at רש"י. Rashi. אין מוסרת עצמה לביאה. ein moseret atzmah l'biah.
רש"י Rashi says, let's read both רש"י. Rashi. שיודעת טעם ביאה, sheyoda'at
ta'am biah, כלומר מאי היא ביאה klomar mai hi biah שתדע לספר
דברים בשוק. sheteda l'saper devarim bashuk. Right? She's going to go up
and blab because doesn't have discretion. But what is she going to
be blabbing about? You know, they have some story sometimes, right? Whatever,
you know, oh, I saw mommy kissing the grocer, you know, or
I saw daddy kissing the babysitter or something like that. So you
usually can figure out something's going on there even though all they
say is kissing or whatever, right? But but that's the point, they
have to know enough to be so that they're reporting something. But
אינה מוסרת עצמה לביאה, einah moseret atzmah l'biah, מתוך קוטן עדיין לא
לבשה יצר. mitoch kotan adayin lo lavsha yetzer. כל כך אין כאן
משום דעת קלה kol kach ein kan mishum da'at kala שלא תהא
נוחה להתפתות. shelo tehei nucha l'hitpateh. Which also by the way says
that we're not really concerned about abuse and about rape. Okay, so
she's not going to willingly participate in the act. She'll know enough
to blab but not enough to be a participant. Okay, and therefore
that makes it better than two normally case of two women. And
again shows by the way not only are we not only concerned
about a rape, it sounds like we're not concerned about rape at
all, right, because otherwise who cares about מוסרת עצמה לביאה? moseret atzmah
l'biah? I mean, sadly we know that, you know, when children are
abused, you know, they get chained into silence, so then that's not
a concern here. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. הגדילו זה ישן בכסותו. higdilu
zeh yashen b'ksuto. Once the kids are older, although parent and child
can, a mother and a son and a father and a daughter
can have ייחוד yichud and even sleep together in the same bed,
and even actually like without without clothes on. Okay, it says once
they are get older they have to they can also still share
bed but they have to have some type of nightclothes on. So
וכמה, vechama, how much older is older? אמר רבא בר אבא אמר
רב אסי, Amar Rava bar Abba amar Rav Assi,
תינוקת tinokes is a whole big debate about what the גירסא girsa
here is, we're just going to read the גירסא girsa in our
גמרא. Gemara. תינוקת בת תשע שנים ויום אחד, tinokes bat tesha shanim
v'yom echad, a a young girl if she's nine once she's nine
years old and a day then the father can't sleep with her
naked, and תינוק בן שתים עשרה שנים ויום אחד, tinok ben shtaim
esre shanim v'yom echad, and a boy once he's twelve years old
and a day then the mother can't sleep with him naked. It's
interesting, that's different. Right? I mean what's that assuming? Is that assuming
that the father might take more advantage of his daughter than the
mother her son? Which, you know, you sort of understand that again
because the man can more- goes back to our question again, rape
or seduction and and so on. But anyway, that's the initial assertion.
איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say, תינוקת בת שתים עשרה שנים ויום
אחד, tinokes bat shtaim esre shanim v'yom echad, תינוק בן שלש עשרה
ויום אחד. tinok ben shlosh esre v'yom echad. So that's the standard
like parallel, right, בר ובת מצווה. bar v'bat mitzvah. That's when they
can't. Okay. Which then the question is, is that because then there's
once it's בר ובת מצווה bar v'bat mitzvah that's linked with, associated
with physical maturity? And then there's a sense about maybe there are,
you know, the concern that they'll have sex is more present just
because, you know, of the physical maturity of their body? Or is
it also because now that they're an adult, you know, they're part
of- they're sort of seen as a more of an independent entity
and therefore also have to be- responsible for the laws of ייחוד?
yichud? Well it seems more the former right, because certainly you have
to look at it from the parents' perspective ענין inyan anyway so
it seems that it's more the former that then they're of an
age of physical maturity. And that's when the גמרא Gemara now elaborates
and the גמרא Gemara says אלו בן תשע שנים ויום אחד וזה
וזה כדי שיהיו שדיים נכונים ושערך צימיח.
eilu ben tisha shanim veyom
echad vezeh vezeh kedei sheyihiyu shadayim nechonim us'arech tzimayach.
And even when they reach that age, okay, it's only a problem
once their body has actually reached physical maturity. And the גמרא Gemara
describes it in terms of the girl, okay, the breasts have developed
and presumably the pubic hair, okay, but if they haven't had those
signs of maturity it's presumed it's not a concern. They had it
earlier. And it had... right, so that's going to be the next,
the other question. רש"י Rashi says, one minute,
one minute, no...
yeah, no, no, רש"י Rashi says presumably even if they have those
signs even at an earlier age, it's not a problem. But you're
right, why isn't it just those signs of maturity? The other point
of course is that the גמרא Gemara has now completely shifted back
to the male perspective because it's only describing the maturity the physical
maturity of the young girl, not of the young boy, right? It's
got a פסוק, pasuk, it's got a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel
for that, but nevertheless it is, you know, what could be expected
completely now shifting to the male perspective and the male gaze here
and only looking at it in terms of the girl. Wasn't
it talking about the father before? It was talking about both... no,
it was talking about the father and the daughter and the mother
and her son. So it didn't give a parallel what would be
the maturity of the son, physical maturity, right? It's only describing that
in terms of the daughter. אמר רבין בר פפא אמר רב חסדא
לא שנו אלא שאינה בושה לעמוד לפניו ערומה. Amar Raffin bar Pappa
amar Rav Chisda lo shanu ela she'eina bosha la'amod lefanav aruma. Now
here's Michael addressing your issue to some degree, there's some times even
at a younger age it could be a concern. When is it
okay at a younger age or without that degree of physical development?
That's if, again, now we're totally shifting to father and daughter, we've
totally shifted to the total male perspective, that's only when the daughter,
but again parallel would be true about a son, only when the
daughter would be afraid to be naked in front of her father.
And not afraid, embarrassed to be naked in front of her
father. אבל בושה לעמוד לפניו ערומה אסור. Aval bosha la'amod lefanav aruma
assur. Why? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? יצר עלה בה. Yetzer ala bah.
So now you see that she is of an age of sexual
having some sexual desire or sexual feelings, she understands what it is
to be naked in front of a member of the opposite sex,
even a parent. And so once there's that reality there is a
concern maybe more that something will happen. So again, by the way,
notice, right, the total concern is in terms of consensual sex, not
in terms of forced sex, right? So once the other party has
the יצר, yetzer, just like the other discussion about the young child
together with the woman, you know, getting rid of ייחוד, yichud, now
there's a concern. But when they could have been abused and taken
advantage of and they were physically mature, that wasn't a concern. Okay.
So, alright. So anyways it's very interesting about dealing with realities of,
you know, some of this might feel weird to us. Really, like
even 10 years old, a 10-year-old daughter naked in a bed together
with her father, like, you know, we might feel that that's very
inappropriate. But you know there are different societies that have different norms
and realities. And the גמרא Gemara says, yeah, okay, it's not saying
it's always appropriate, you know, there are times when you know in
these cases when you are embarrassed to be naked or a certain
degree of age and development, but in other times there was a
more, I guess, you know, physical intimacy and the גמרא Gemara felt
that that was appropriate. So I don't know how people are feeling
reading this, like, you know, are they feeling like, oh that's nice
that the גמרא Gemara is able
to sort of deal with realities and not be not have like
this hyper, you know,
like the word isn't sensitivity but you know hypervigilance around these types
of things? That can acknowledge, you know, these realities for what they
were cause I'm sure 99 times out of 100 they were innocent
and they were the reality. Right? Or are we like are we
like saying are we like reading this and saying like, I can't
believe it, like, you know, some really bad stuff could happen here
and how is the גמרא Gemara not concerned about that? So I
think it's interesting, you know, when you look at it with different
eyes.
I'm sorry but
I haven't gotten past even the ייחוד yichud thing with your daughter,
like, you know, at any point. I mean forget about sleeping with
them. Like we have it before.
Right, that's your perspective. Somebody else might say what you never heard
about child abuse? You never heard about, you know, fathers are, you
know, there are lots of cases about fathers, you know, sexually abusing
their daughters, right? So that's the question. So do you go ahead
and make תקנות takanot for that, you know, whatever it is one
out of a thousand cases,
right? It happens all the time but it may only happen one
out of a thousand times, I'm making up the number but let's
say, you know, so do you sort of say we can't go
ahead and make תקנות takanot for that and we have to let
people live their, which is what I think the גמרא Gemara is
saying, right?
So the crazy thing is נשי ישראל על עריות neshei Yisrael al
arayot we're making תקנות, takanot, we say לא חשדו ישראל על משכב
זכר. lo hashdu Yisrael al mishkav zachar.
Right, why don't we just say it about all the עריות? arayot?
I'm saying that... right, obviously.
So some things we're concerned about and some things we're not. Alright,
so let's continue. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, now here's a
story. רב אחא בר אבא איקלע לבי רב חסדא. Rav Acha bar
Abba ikla lebei Rav Chisda. רב אחא בר אבא Rav Achah bar
Abba came to the house of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, חתניה, chasnei,
his son-in-law.
שקלה לבת ברתיה, shaklei levas barteih,
he took his granddaughter, his son-in-law's daughter,
אותיב בכנפיה, oseiv beichnafeih, put her like in his cloak or sat
her on his lap. אמר ליה, amar leih, so his son-in-law said
to him, לא סברת לה מר דאשת איש, lo savar lah mar
de'eishes ish, what, don't you realize she's a married woman? Our five-year-old
granddaughter.
We don't know how old she is, but child, like she's
young. She's twelve. Okay, she's, we're going to see in a minute
she was a קטנה. ktana. Okay. What? Don't you realize that we
married her off already? So getting us back to the theme of
מסכת קידושין. Maseches Kiddushin. אמר ליה, amar leih, hah,
you what? You married her off? עברת לך אדרב, avarta lach adei-Rav,
you went against the ruling of רב, Rav, דאמר רב יהודה אמר
רב ואיתימא רבי אלעזר אסור לאדם שיקדש את בתו כשהיא קטנה עד
שתגדל ותאמר בפלוני אני רוצה. de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav ve'iseima Rabbi
Elazar assur le'adam she'yekadesh es bito kshe'hi ktana ad she'tisgadel ve'somar be'ploni
ani rotza. Didn't you learn this earlier in the מסכתא, masechta, beginning
of the second פרק? perek? We said that a man is not
allowed to marry off his daughter when she's a minor. You have
to wait till she grows up and she can choose the man
she wants to be married to. So how did you marry her
off? Okay, so it's always the best defense is a good offense.
Okay.
אמר, amar, so he said, מר נמי עבר ליה אדשמואל. mar nami
avar leih adei-Shmuel. Okay, but you, fine, I did something wrong, but
you're going against what שמואל Shmuel teaches, דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, שמואל
Shmuel says, אין משתמשין באשה. ein mishtamshin be'isha. You're not allowed to
make use of the service of a woman, which seems to be
meaning to serve as an attendant, like you know, they would have
these female attendants or whatever and שמואל Shmuel would say that's inappropriate.
Okay, and here, now it's not exactly the same. He's not having
her attend to him. He's just sitting her on the lap, but
it's the same point. Like we have to keep our distance even
if it's something seems innocent like, okay, she's, you know, she's the
maid, she's serving the meals or whatever. This isn't sexual. And again,
notice שמואל, Shmuel, right, is hypersensitive. Like, you know, doesn't want to
be with an animal, doesn't want to be with his daughter, doesn't
want to be whatever. So you can't have a woman doing the
domestic service around the house. Again, I don't know exactly what the
parameters are because the whole משנה mishna in כתובות Kesuvos talked about
the woman bringing in various maidservants and so on. But whatever. Maybe
some type of attending. Mostly the maidservants the woman would bring in
would do the back-office stuff, like would work on the sewing and
the whatever. That'd be okay. But actually be attending to the needs
of the man and especially sometimes those needs were pouring a bath
and all those other types of things. שמואל Shmuel says don't tell
me it's all innocent. Maybe it is innocent or whatever but we
gotta not allow it. שמואל's Shmuel very consistent. Okay. So he says,
so if you're not allowed to do that, you can't sit your
granddaughter on your lap, right, even your married granddaughter. By the way,
here's a question. It sounds like if she weren't married, it wouldn't
be a problem. At what age is there a ייחוד yichud problem?
Right, it gets back to these sort of earlier גמרא, Gemara, right,
about the, that גמרא Gemara was talking about sleeping naked with your
daughter. But at what age is there a ייחוד yichud problem? How
old, if the girl is three is there a ייחוד yichud problem?
Is there with any girl, with any woman, right, or with any
man? Right, does it go by the age of ביאה, biah, nine-year-old
boy and a three-year-old girl? Right, does it go with, you know,
בר ובת מצוה? bar ve'bas mitzvah? What age do these types of
things start becoming a problem? Okay. Here, it sounded like he was
only giving him a hard time because she was married, right? Okay,
so those are other very interesting questions. Anyway, he said, look, you,
so you're, I shouldn't have married her. You shouldn't have sat her
on your lap. You know, שמואל Shmuel makes all these, all these
safeguards. So he says, אמר ליה אנא כאידך דשמואל סבירא לי. amar
leih ana k'idach de'Shmuel sevira li. No, no, no, I go like
this other teaching of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, הכל לשם
שמים. hakol leshem shamayim.
If it's all, if it's, if what you're doing is for the
sake of heaven, if your כוונה's kavana in the right place, you
don't have to worry about it. Now talk about two approaches of
שמואל Shmuel that are like completely diametrically opposite. One is all of
these safeguards, but if your כוונה's kavana לשם שמים, leshem shamayim, if
your pure intent, you don't have to worry about it. Now what
does that allow? First of all, look at רש"י. Rashi. הכל לשם
שמים. hakol leshem shamayim. ואין דעתי אחריה לחיבת אישות. ve'ein da'ati achareiha
le'chibas ishus. I'm not doing it in a sexual way. That's how
I'll interpret that. אלא לחיבת קורבה. ela le'chibas kurva. I'm doing it
in a, you know, as a, I'm a grandfather. Because of love
and, you know,
and warmth and so on. Not the word I'm looking for. But
anyway, ולעשות קורת רוח לאמה כשאני מחבב את בתה. vela'asos koras ruach
le'imah k'she'ani mechabev es bitah. To show her mother how much I
love her, her daughter, right? A grandfather hugs and kisses his granddaughter.
That's not sexual. I mean, you know, what type of person thinks
that that's sexual? So first of all, that's important because, you know,
sometimes פוסקים poskim talk as if there's only two types of touch.
Right? There's neutral touch and sexual touch. You know, there's a lot
of touch that's between neutral and sexual, right? Comforting, loving, or whatever
without being sexual. Number one. Number two though, is, is this idea
of הכל לשם שמים hakol leshem shamayim is very interesting. It gets
into the whole discussion, because this is no longer a question of
ייחוד yichud in a way. This is a question about touch if
you really think about it. Right? And so that's really the question
that a number of ראשונים rishonim say, is there an איסור דרבנן
issur de'rabbanan of neutral touch between a man and a woman he's
not married to? Okay, and let's say a woman who's a נדה,
niddah, a married woman. Fine. It's an איסור עריות, issur arayos, no
problem, understood. Neutral touch, a handshake, right? So a number of, you
know, that's the whole, right, a number of פוסקים poskim think, like,
as many of the common discourse you hear is, oh, that's אסור
דרבנן, assur de'rabbanan, but maybe... Could be overridden for the sake of
כבוד הבריות *Kevod Habriyos* so in a business situation and somebody be
embarrassed, you don't stick out your hand, you don't shake their hand,
you don't whatever, etcetera etcetera. I don't know if people heard there
was this whole interesting case in France, did people hear about this?
These two Muslim boys, where was it? Not in France, was it
in France? I know, it was in Switzerland. I think Sweden or
Switzerland, one of those SW places. Anyway, the custom was that all
the kids would shake their teacher's hand and that was seen as
a very important cultural sign of respect. And these two Muslim boys,
where was it? Switzerland. These two Muslim boys refused to shake their
teacher's
hand. So the school said okay, but then you don't shake your
men teacher's hand either, we'll be consistent. Anyway, then the public got
wind of this and there was a huge outcry and the court
basically ruled that they have to shake their teacher's hand. And then
the whole big question
about anyway, we could have that other discussion about. Anyway, the point
is, so one approach is there's some people that will never shake
anybody's hand, there are some people that will say okay, it's מותר
*Muttar* because of כבוד הבריות *Kevod Habriyos*, but they'll wait till the
man will wait till the woman sticks out her hand, which is
sometimes כבוד הבריות *Kevod Habriyos* to anticipate it also. Anyway, but a
number of ראשונים *Rishonim* and פוסקים poskim *Poskim* based on this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* and parallel גמרות *Gemoros* say if it's not sexual, there's
no technical איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan *Issur D'rabonon*. If you know that
this type of a touch will lead to הרהורים *Hirhurim* or some
sexual charge, then don't do it. But if you know that it's
going to be completely neutral, then there's no problem. It doesn't need
an override, fundamentally there's not a problem if you can trust yourself
and you know that it's a neutral type of a touch. Which
me as a Rabbi, that's always a challenge because on the one
hand, so I'm totally fine with that, I'm prepared to even stick
out my hand and shake, I don't wait for somebody to stick
out their hand or whatever. But then you don't know, is the
person going to be offended if you do stick out your hand
or if you don't stick out your hand? What, I thought you
were an Orthodox Rabbi, what are you doing sticking out your hand?
Okay, anyway fine. But anyway, so this is interesting here because this
is no longer really a ייחוד yichud *Yichud* case, but it is
interesting how does it work together with other statements of שמואל *Shmuel*?
שמואל *Shmuel* about all of his big ייחוד yichud. *Yichud* limits, all
of the fact that אין משתמשין באשה *Ein Mishtamshin B'isha*, maybe שמואל
*Shmuel* is saying both things. Maybe שמואל *Shmuel* is saying more like
that override approach. He's saying yes, there are all of these parameters,
those are the default parameters, but in special cases, if you know
that you are okay and you can be trusted and it's not
a concern, then it's okay. Right?
So that's how you
balance those two, meaning you can balance it by saying there are
no formal איסורים *Issurim*, just use your best judgment. Or you could
say no, there are these formal parameters, but in special cases if
you know that you're a special case, then it's okay, and that
shifts
the dynamic of what your point of departure is with these things.
Right, but getting to the point of you deciding whether you're okay
is a really complicated thing because if that was it all along,
then
exactly, how about that תלמיד *Talmid* that was לגלג *Melagleg* and thought
how could anybody have that יצר הרע yetzer hara *Yetzer Hara* and
then they're just not being honest with their own יצר הרע *Yetzer
Hara*. Right, exactly, I understand the problem with that. So it's an
interesting question how much this הכל לשם שמים *Ha-kol L'shem Shamayim* is
for צדיקים גמורים *Tzaddikim Gemurim* who know they won't have הרהור *Hirhur*
or how much is it more of a really guideline in actual
practice.
Also, for we're all at a place where we're all shaking hands
and the poor person who for shaking hands is a problem for
whatever they decide that it is a problem with them, then everyone
knows
what their יצר הרע *Yetzer Hara* is. It
does, exactly, exactly. Alright, so let's now we move on, so now
the final דף *Daf* here or עמוד *Amud*. לא ילמד אדם רווק
lo yilamed adam ravak... סופרים *Lo yilamed adam ravak sofrim*. A single
man should not be a school teacher. It's a funny grammar. He
should not teach סופרים *Sofrim*, but he should not be, meaning סופרים
*Sofrim* is it means school teacher somehow that לא ילמד סופרים *lo
yilamed sofrim*, he's not teaching scribes. Okay, but anyway, don't be a
teacher and be a school teacher if he's
single.
רווק ravak *Ravak* means never
married.
ולא תלמד אשה סופרים *V'lo telamed isha sofrim*, and a woman should
not be a school teacher, which is of course ironic because ninety-eight
percent of the school teachers are women, of the younger grades, are
women, lower school. רבי Rebbi אליעזר אומר אף מי שאין לו אשה
לא ילמד סופרים *Rabbi Eliezer omer af mi she-ein lo isha lo
yilamed sofrim*. Even a man who currently does not have a wife,
which could mean he was married and he's divorced or his wife
died or we'll see another possibility in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay,
so meaning you could have said well if once a person has
had an opportunity to
have had a wife and has been sexually active he's less concerned,
but he says no, even if you currently don't have a wife
it's a problem. So according to all of this, the only person
who can be a school teacher is a married man. And by
the way, I do find this very strange. Why is a married
man—it doesn't say a single woman can't be a school teacher, it
says a woman. Why is a married man safer than a married
woman? Right? A married woman we say בעלה בעיר, ba'alah ba'ir you
know, even if her husband isn't right there, she's concerned about her
husband, right? Is it because we are—again, this assumption that women are
easier to seduce than men? But I don't—well I don't exactly get
it. Now we'll see in the גמרא Gemara what are we afraid
of. Are we afraid that they're going to abuse—they're going to abuse
the children? The גמרא's Gemara, going to say no. So let's just
wait a minute.
Are we assuming that they're both male and female students?
So let's take a look. We'll see what the גמרא Gemara, says,
okay? Because it's not going to be about the students. Okay, לא
ילמד רווק תינוקות. Lo yilmad ravak tinokot. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, okay, לא ירעה רווק בהמה lo yir'eh ravak behemah ולא ישנו
שני רווקים בטלית אחת. velo yishnu shenei ravakim betallit achat. So a
single man or an unmarried man, a never married, should not be
a school teacher, and two unmarried men should not be in one—no,
they're both shepherds.
Right, sleep under—or well—right,
sleep under one blanket, וחכמים מתירים, vachachamim matirin, the חכמים Chachamim allow
it. So going back a little bit to the issue before about
who's going to be a shepherd, for him it's not—anybody can't, but
it can't be at least a single man. Okay, so let's take
a look at the גמרא, Gemara very interesting גמרא, Gemara. very interesting
משנה, Mishnah, let's unpack it. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason
that you can't be a school teacher, an unmarried man? אילימא משום
ינוקי, Ilima mishum yenokei, the children? והתניא, Vehatanya, אמרו לו לרבי יהודה,
amru lo leRabbi Yehuda, לא נחשדו ישראל על משכב זכור ועל הבהמה,
lo neshchedu Yisrael al mishkav zachur ve'al habehemah,
that the response to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about the sharing the
blanket or being a shepherd is they said that, you know, Jews
are not suspect of sleeping with animals or of two men sleeping
together. Right, very interesting in terms of the contemporary obviously, you know,
issues around gay sex and הלכה halacha and so on. I'll talk
in a minute about that. Okay, so therefore why would we be
afraid? Now the presumption being that the kids that are going to
חדר cheder are only boys. Only boys get formal education. So what
are we concerned about? Right? We can't be concerned about the kids
because we're not concerned that they're going to, you know, engage in
sex with another man or a male, even a boy. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא רווק משום אמהות דינוקי, ela ravak mishum immahot
deyenokei, a single man can't be a teacher because of the mothers
who will bring the kids to school, the ינוקי, yenokei, ואשה משום
אבות דינוקי, ve'ishah mishum avot deyenokei, and the woman can't be a
teacher because of the fathers that will bring people to school. You
want to have a conference with the parent, so you know, you
go and have a little private conference and then who knows what
happens, right? Or there's too much mingling and too much getting to,
you know, opportunities there. Right? I mean it happens also, especially divorced
parents or whatever, it's not like these things don't happen. So, but
the interesting thing that I still want to know is, so first
of all this isn't exactly a ייחוד yichud, concern. We're going to
see this in the גמרא. Gemara You could say it's a concern,
don't allow this, it will lead to ייחוד. yichud But it's
more than that. It's more like it will lead to sex, right?
It's not like—oh, I mean you could say it two ways: oh,
it's אסור assur because they'll have a conference together in a room
and that will be ייחוד, yichud and then we'll have a ייחוד
yichud איסור. issur. I don't think we're saying that. I don't think
it's a גזירה לייחוד. gezeirah leyichud. I think it's like these types
of interactions will actually
prevent—present temptations and lead to sex. But the question I still ask
is—and we're obviously in a segregated society, we want to avoid these
types of regular mixings which will happen every single day when they
bring the kids to school. But I still want to know why
it's less of a problem for a married man than a married
woman. Right? Why is the married man not going to—less of a
problem of seducing the mothers, you know, than the married woman in
terms of being seduced by the father, I don't know what—or seducing
the father, I don't know why there's a difference there. Yes.
What's the
difference if you're a shopkeeper? Men and women tend to be your
shopkeeper. A lot. Why shouldn't that be—? Men and women go to
a shopkeeper.
That's a good
question. I guess it's
because—yeah, I don't know. I think if it's because of the
opportunity—I guess it's the circumstantial opportunities that there are sometimes fewer people
around, like in shops it's regular like פתח פתוח לרשות הרבים. petach
patuach lereshut harabbim. All the other kids? Yeah,
it's true, it's true.
Drop off and pick up the
kids at the same time roughly. What? Yeah. But that's with individual
parent-teacher?
What
are you saying?
Not with individual parent-teacher. I mean, have you ever been to a
school where you had to wait 15-20 minutes?
It's the equivalent—alright.
Yeah, you know, I
guess they aren't around a round table.
I don't know, maybe it's that parents and teachers have more intimate
conversations. Like I need to talk to you about your child, you
know, and somehow whereas shopkeepers it's much more—remains very professional and transactional
and business-like, right? Look, I don't know. I definitely have heard of
stories that this happens, right, with parents and teachers. And I don't
hear about this with shopkeepers. So, right? You do? Okay.
I guess there's stories about the mailman, but that's like—okay. But that's
the point. I think it's like what circumstances allow for more interactions
than others, you know? Yeah.
And just in the married man versus married woman thing, I feel
like we're really worried about the men. So if the man who's
the teacher is married, we're less worried about him. and but if
there's a woman, we don't know who the men are who are
maybe dropping off children or who are coming in.
Right, so the man might be a single man and then he
might more, right, I think the משנה Mishnah does not incorporate the
teaching of because I'm also asked myself whatever happened about like בעלה
בעיר type of cases. I don't know if the משנה Mishnah is
fully incorporated that you know that teaching which was an אמוראי amoraic
teaching, but I think you're right. It starts with the idea that
the man is the concern, right? Anyway, that's very interesting. Okay, so
that's that. Now how about this other issue? רבי אלעזר אומר אף
מי שאין לו, Rabbi Elazar omer af mi she'ein lo,
even somebody who doesn't have a wife, woman. איבעיא להו מי שאין
לו אשה כלל, Ibeya lehu mi she'ein lo isha klal,
does he mean that if you if he doesn't have a wife
at all, meaning he was married but now he's divorced or or
widowed? או דילמא בשאינה שרויה אצלו, o dilma b'she'eina sheruya etzlo,
or maybe even if he is married, it's a problem if for
some reason they're separated or she's off on some vacation. So when
his wife is off vacation on a vacation somewhere, he has to
also take a leave of absence. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and
hear, אף מי שיש לו ואינה שרויה אצלו לא ילמד סופרים. af
mi sheyesh lo v'eina sheruya etzlo lo yilamed soferim. So we have
a ברייתא braita that says that explicitly that according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, okay, I'm sorry, not was it רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, right, that even if he's not currently with
his wife, we're afraid that he'll be he'll give into temptation.
Could be, although I haven't actually she's on a could be. Maybe,
I don't know, it's could be, could be. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר
לא ירעה, Rabbi Yehuda omer lo yireh, now this issue about being
a shepherd and or or sleeping together under one blanket, two men.
תניא אמרו לו לרבי יהודה לא נחשדו ישראל על משכב זכר ועל
הבהמה. Tanya amru lo l'Rabbi Yehuda lo nechshadu Yisrael al mishkav zachar
v'al habehemah. So they said, well, we're not concerned about ייחוד yichud
and these types of situations or even sleeping together and so on
when it comes to you know animals or two men. Now this
is I'll just say one word about this, obviously very sensitive and
important topic. Say two things. Number one is that I think it
does show that חז״ל, Chazal, I mean, okay, there is the position
of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but I think this חז״ל Chazal is
the very sort of dominant voice and shows that they understood thought
that sex between two men was as unnatural as sex between a
person and an animal, which is type of thing you hear today
from some people, right? The only real sex is heterosexual and it
raises questions about how one conceptualizes, right, after all of the heterosexual
forbidden sexes, you know it ends by saying by talking in the
תורה, Torah, two men and then a man and an animal, right?
So that's just the order but it all also under this big
umbrella of forbidden sexual acts. So it raises an interesting conceptual question
of how חז״ל Chazal thought about that whole phenomenon. Now the so
on the one hand that's deeply disturbing from our contemporary sensibilities. On
the other hand, it's very interesting because it means if they didn't
think it was if they thought it was completely unnatural and nothing
that you know a normal good normal יהודי Yehudi would be it's
something that the גויים goyim do, not that יהודים Yehudim do, it
also meant that they didn't see a reason to legislate about it.
Which raises really interesting questions nowadays, which are questions that I get,
which is like can a gay man be in ייחוד yichud with
another man or another heterosexual or a heterosexual man or another gay
man? Is there a an איסור ייחוד? issur yichud? Now you could
also say, wow, you shouldn't be tempting yourself, but let's say it's
you know it's a case where you're not tempted, it's a pal,
it's a friend, nobody is sexually attracted to the other person, but
is there an איסור ייחוד, issur yichud, right? So you know and
and here it sounds like no, we didn't make that, we didn't
make it because we didn't think that it was a concern. What
if it is a concern? Does that create an איסור ייחוד? issur
yichud? So that's discussed in the פוסקים poskim about whether once there
is if there is a reality of a concern, the פוסקים Poskim
say if you're dealing with a certain man who actually was known
to have engaged in sex with other men, then obviously he shouldn't
be in ייחוד yichud and he shouldn't certainly shouldn't sleep under the
same blanket with another man, but is that because of there's a
formal rabbinic prohibition or are we saying no, it never was legislated,
but even though it wasn't legislated, you don't do things that are
opening yourself up to you know temptation, right? It's just not being
responsible. So interesting questions about how to think about whether ever any
rabbinic legislation around these types of areas or because they thought that
it was just so unheard of, right, that therefore they didn't they
never legislated it. Yes.
Do you think the latter approach then
you need to model your rules that you that you created after
ייחוד Yichud rules or is it just like a completely separate thing
that you say, well, here's a new situation, let's
exactly that.
Meaning if you say there was no formal legislation, then the answer
would be you know if you feel that there's some degree of
sexual attraction or whatever, some degree of concern, then obviously you shouldn't
do it the same way if you have a you know if
you have a יצר הרע for you know for cheeseburgers, don't go
into McDonalds to order a coke, right? Nobody's saying there's some formal
איסור דרבנן Issur d'Rabbanan you're being over on, but but don't be
irresponsible, right? But then you sort of judge case by case, right,
in terms of it's not exactly that you know now if you
again sometimes as you pointed out when we began the ייחוד Yichud
discussion, sometimes because of the nature of sexual desire and so on,
it means making certain formal things you know and not you know
and realizing that we don't always know exactly. how we're going to
act in certain situations. But the point being that we would not
follow formal rules, you know, it would be like any other area
which חז״ל Chazal did not legislate, but you should not be exposing
yourself to temptation, you know, you shouldn't be irresponsible about your הלכה
Halacha responsibilities, you know, and exposing yourself to temptation and you should
have to judge those cases.
It's interesting, you think the פוסקים Poskim might be on both sides
of this, meaning
yeah, there are פוסקים that feel that once this is a reality
of a concern, for people for whom this is a concern, they
then the formal rules do kick in and they become formal rules,
and others say there are never any formal rules, it's just like
don't, like I said, don't, you know, expose yourself to temptation.
But two other questions. One is, would it be okay for a
gay man to be in ייחוד Yichud with a woman if he
doesn't have a...
yeah, so that's also an interesting question and whatever, מחלוקת. machlokes.
The last thing, yes, a special thing, why is it זכור Zachor
instead of זכר? Zachar?
Yeah, I never got that either, why משכב זכור. mishkav zachor. I
think because otherwise it could be זכר Zachar and so... I think
it's just, I don't know, I'm sure there's some grammatical explanation which
I don't know. Okay, next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, כל שעסקיו
עם
הנשים,
kol she-asakav
im ha-nashim, since we're talking about being a school teacher and so
on, okay now we get to, now we sort of broaden the
discussion, okay, about tempting types of situations.
Yes, so how do we פסקן pasken for the previous...
well, we פסקן pasken like the חכמים Chachamim against רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. Okay.
Yeah, so לא ילמד אדם רווק...
oh no, you mean in the first case. Yeah, the רמב״ם Rambam
פסקנס paskens that way. Of course, well how do we therefore allow
there to be female school teachers nowadays? I don't know, I mean
people must say, you know, in the circumstances where you're dealing with
a large school, you know what I mean, and like I mean
I'm sure there's other teachers around or whatever, I'm sure that the...
I haven't looked at the literature but I'm sure there's an explanation
about how our circumstances are significantly different, right? And one also gets
a sense, like is this the same type of formal איסור Issur
as like the איסור ייחוד, Issur Yichud, right? Or is this obviously
a statement about a certain circumstances and guidelines around, you know, and
how much is there a technical איסור דרבנן to be doing this,
right? Okay, so those are good questions. Okay, כל שעסקיו עם הנשים
לא יתייחד עם הנשים. kol she-asakav im ha-nashim lo yityached im ha-nashim.
Anybody who deals, whose business is with women, meaning I don't know,
he's a dressmaker, he's a jewelry maker, whatever, he should not be
in ייחוד Yichud with women. So there's an interesting debate between רש״י
Rashi and
רמב״ם Rambam
whether this means... the way רש״י Rashi explains it is, is that
normally a man can't be with two women, but a man can
be with three women. And therefore, but this guy is always around
with women, he's a dressmaker, whatever, and he's all, you know, so
he obviously has developed a very, like boundaries have gone down, right?
He's always there with the women fixing their dresses and so on,
he shouldn't even be with three women because there's going to be
too much of an opportunity there for
him to do his profession.
Yeah, to make sure there's another man around I guess. Anyway, that's
the way תוספות, Tosafot, רש״י Rashi reads it. But the important part
about that is that רש״י Rashi says as a general rule there's
no ייחוד Yichud with one man and three women. רמב״ם Rambam and
תוספות Tosafot say the same way there's ייחוד Yichud with one man
and two women, there's ייחוד Yichud with one man and three women,
okay? And with four women and five women, there's actually always going
to be ייחוד Yichud unless you have two men. So therefore what
it's saying is even the dressmaker who needs to do it for
פרנסה, parnassah, you might think that he's more inured to this because
this is an everyday situation, even he the normal הלכות halachos of
ייחוד Yichud, still apply and he has to make sure there's another
man around. Okay, but the interesting corollary of this discussion is, is
there ייחוד yichud, with one man and three women? We פסקן pasken
mostly, the אשכנזים Ashkenazim פסקן pasken like רש״י Rashi that with one
man and three women there isn't ייחוד, but some understand that there
is. Okay, so the גמרא says like this.
Okay, now we go on. ולא ילמד אדם בנו אומנות הנשים, v'lo
yelamed adam b'no umanut hanashim, a man should not teach his son
a trade that is, you know, that deals with women because of
exposing to these types of temptations. רבי מאיר אומר לעולם ילמד אדם
בנו אומנות נקייה וקלה. Rabbi Meir omer l'olam yilamed adam b'no umanut
nekiyah v'kalah. You should always teach your son a clean and easy
job, shouldn't get your hands too dirty, shouldn't be too laborious, should
be whatever. Why? Should that be the אומנות? umanut? Maybe you make
more money if you do something that's more demanding. Because here's what
רבי says... ויתפלל למי שהעושר והנכסים שלו. v'yitpallel l'mi sheha-osher vehanechasim shelo.
And you know what, when it comes to how much money you'll
make, pray to God, pray to the one who has the wealth,
שאין אומנות שאין בה עניות ועשירות. she'ein umanut she'ein bah aniyut v'ashirut.
There's no job, you know, that does not have people that are
rich and people that are poor. Okay? You've got stockbrokers that make
millions and you have stockbrokers that barely put food on the table.
שלא עניות מן האומנות ולא עשירות מן האומנות, shelo aniyut min ha-umanut
v'lo ashirut min ha-umanut,
because poverty and wealth is not a function of your trade, אלא
הכל לפי זכותו, ela hakol lefi zechuto,
it all is about your merit. Now what does merit mean? You
would think like if you're righteous or not, and are you being
מתפלל mitpallel or not. תוספות Tosafot very interestingly reinterprets this to mean
your מזל, mazel, based on another גמרא which was like... Really, זכות
zchut and מזל mazzal I thought were like the exact opposite.
Okay, but anyway, anyway רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is look,
you obviously can't say I'm not going to work, like the old
joke about the guy with the lottery ticket, everybody knows that joke?
The no, the guy goes and he prays to God and says
רבונו של עולם Ribbono shel Olam all my life I've believed in
you, I've you know I've דאוונד, davened, I've kept all the מצוות.
mitzvot. Once, once in my life like why didn't I ever win
the lottery? And then this voice comes out from heaven and says
idiot, buy a ticket.
So, so you know so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying look
you gotta have a job, right? Like you know you're not going
to money isn't going to fall from heaven. But pick a job
that's going to let you sit and learn תורה, Torah, presumably that's
his point, that's the way the מהרש"א Maharsha says it, that's not
going to be too demanding, that's not going to get you into
uncomfortable situations, that's not going to get your hands dirty. And in
terms of how much money you make, that'll be up to God.
So it's all going to be up to God, so you should
get the easiest job possible that's going to you know not get
you into trouble and not be too hard and give you time
to learn תורה. Torah. Jacob you had a quest- oh no, Dov
you had a question?
Yeah, just the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, when you contrast it
to the previous משנה, Mishnah, I mean you would think that the
that the teacher would come under the אסקפיא מנשים askafya minashim if
that's the situation. But no, there we specify only רווק and not
someone who's married is not that's not the problem.
Right. So I think that this is taking it one- well first
of all it's a little bit go- right, I think it's like
taking it one step further. I mean that's עסק עם נשים, esek
im nashim, the mothers drop the kids off and then they leave.
There's like another מדרגה madreigah for the dressmaker, you know, the jewelry
maker and so on, right? So I don't think it's the same
degree but nevertheless it's like, you know these are all like degrees
of preference, right? So it would be preferable certainly not to be
a dressmaker, better not also to be a school tea- I mean,
you know, but anyway, but עסק עם נשים esek im nashim is
a higher degree of involvement than the schoolteacher. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אומר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer ראית מימיך חיה ועוף שיש להם
אומנות? ra'ita miyamecha chayah va'of she-yesh lahem umanut?
Have you ever seen in your life like an animal or a
bird that goes through you know they get dressed up in their
business suits and they go to their jobs? והם מתפרנסים שלא בצער,
v'hem mitparnsim shelo b'tza'ar, they manage to get their sustenance without going
to any effort. והלא לא נבראו אלא לשמשני, v'halo lo nivre'u ela
l'shamsheni, and these animals were created to serve me. ואני נבראתי לשמש
את קוני, v'ani nivreti l'shamesh et koni, and I, I have a
greater function on this planet, I'm here to serve God. אינו דין
שאתפרנס שלא בצער? eino din she'etparnes shelo b'tza'ar? So first of all
like why do I have to go to work at all? Why
can't I just go out and eat the grass? Like why do
I have to work harder than these animals? אלא שהרעותי מעשי, ela
she'hare'oti ma'asai, now obviously where do we know that a human being
has to work for their labor? From the first חטא, chet, right?
בזעת אפך תאכל לחם. b'ze'at apecha tochal lechem. אלא שהרעותי מעשי, ela
she'hare'oti ma'asai, my, my deeds were bad because I sinned, okay, וקפחתי
את פרנסתי, v'kippachti et parnasati, and I therefore you know destroyed like
you know injured
my sustenance. Basically because of my sins that's why now I have
to go to work. Does he mean you're not to go to
work? No, he's just he's just pointing out that this is like
a fallen state. It sounds to me like he's coming to reinforce,
again that's a little Christian, anyway it sounds to me that he's
coming to reinforce רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir point. Like don't think like
oh you know of course this is the way the world works,
the world works that you know so what do you mean pray
to God? There are professions that make money and others that don't
and we have to be true to how the world works and
whatever. No, he says the way the world really really works is
really like the animals, that it should just come naturally. This is
all about your sin, so therefore pray to God, focus on like
leading a righteous life, and don't worry too much about your job.
I think it's coming to reinforce רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אבא גוריון
איש צידין אומר משום אבא גוריא Abba Guryon ish tzaidin omer mishum
Abba Gurya לא ילמד אדם את בנו חמר גמל קדר ספן רועה
וחנוני. lo yilammed adam et b'no chammar gamal kaddar sappan ro'eh v'chanvani.
Do not teach your son to be a donkey driver, a camel
driver,
a wagon driver,
or a sailor, or a shepherd, or a storekeeper, שאומנותן אומנות ליסטים
she'umanutan umanut listim because they are they're all robbers. Now what does
it mean that they're all robbers? So רש"י Rashi says they're all
robbers because the animals and the ones that go on a far
away journey whatever they graze in other people's lands, they collect wood
for their fires from other people's lands, you know and so on.
Those are the people that are with their animal you know the
camel and the donkey drivers. And the shepherd and the חנוני chanvani
is also the shepherd and the חנוני chanvani is because you know
רש"י Rashi says yeah exactly weights and measures and all of that.
Okay, but the next line, one minute, רבי יהודה אומר משמו, Rabbi
Yehudah omer mishmo, Rabbi Yehudah says in the name of אבא גוריון,
Abba Guryon, החמרים רובן רשעים, hachammarim rubban resha'im, donkey drivers most of
them are wicked because you know again they go ahead and they
you know graze their donkeys in other people's lands or something of
that nature. והגמלים רובן כשירים, v'hagamalim rubban kshirim, but the camel drivers
most of them are kosher. Why? א' alef because they're out in
the desert so who are they stealing from? and ב' bet רש"י
Rashi says when they're exposed to danger they pray to God, okay,
and they're more and they're פרום-er. frum הספנים רובן חסידים, hasappanim rubban
chasidim, and the boat the sailors I mean you know they're exposed
to all the dangers of the sea, those are really righteous. Okay,
now here's the point- Most
of them are כשר *kosher*. Why? A, because they're out in the
desert, so who are they stealing from? And B, רש״י *Rashi* says
when they're exposed to danger, they pray to God. Okay, and they're
more and they're פרומער *frummer*. הספנים רובם חסידים *hasapanim ruban chasidim*. And
the boat—the sailors, I mean you know, they're exposed to all the
dangers of the sea. Those are really righteous. Okay, now of course
the point—they're the only ones who don't curse.
Exactly. So now the point is that he's now saying something the
exact opposite because the previous statement was was that they're all robbers,
they're all ליסטים *listim*. So that's why the מהרש״א *Maharsha* says that
the statement, the first statement that they're ליסטים *listim* was only going
on the shepherd and the storekeeper, because the shepherd and the storekeeper
have a lot of opportunities of cheating and grazing and all of
that. The people that just, you know, bring donkeys
to to what do you call it, to move wares or whatever
it is or camels and so on, that he's saying don't do
it, not because they're robbers. Don't do it because you know, because
it's a difficult job and you're out of the city and you're
not whatever, you know, and yeah, you're not staying at home and
all those types of concerns. So it's interesting. What are the concerns?
Are the concerns exactly that, you know, of sin or is it
similar to the רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* concerns, at least some of
these, of that it's just not an אומנות קלה ונקייה *umanut kala
u-nekiya*? It's very, very hard and takes you out of, you know,
having a nice home and a stable type of a life and
so on. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. טוב שברופאים לגיהנום
*tov shebi-rofin l'Gehennom*. The best of doctors should go to גיהנום *Gehennom*.
So now why? So רש״י *Rashi* says, if you look at רש״י
*Rashi* right before the lines get wide, why? אינו ירא מן החולי
ומאכלו מאכל בריאים *eino yarei min hacholi umachalo maachal bri'im*. First of
all, because he takes such good care of his own health, I'm
not sure that's always true about doctors. So he thinks like they're
like immortal. Oh, I'm so healthy. ואינו משבר לבו למקום *ve'eino meshaber
libo laMakom*. So it's as opposed to again like the sailors who
are seeing, you know, who are so scared of their lives. Doctors
are too confident about their well-being. Okay, ופעמים שהורג נפשות ויש לו
בידו לרפאות עני ואינו מרפא *u-fe'amim she-horeig nefashot ve-yesh lo b'yado l'rapot
ani ve-eino m'rapei*. Right,
or whatever, they think they're God or they actually cause people to
die because they're not conscientious about their job. So מהרש״א *Maharsha* has
a great read of this line. He says, טוב שברופאים *tov shebi-rofin*.
The doctor who thinks he's the best of the doctors, he's going
to גיהנום *Gehennom*. So that's like such a good life sense. That's
the one that doesn't ask consult and doesn't talk to his colleagues.
It's the one who thinks he's the best is going to גיהנום
*Gehennom*. Okay, והכשר שבטבחים שותפו של עמלק *v'hakasher shebatabachim shutfo shel Amalek*.
And the best of the or the one who looks like he's
a כשר *kosher* butcher, and I mean that like פרומער *frummer*, you
know, whatever, of good character. He's really a partner with עמלק *Amalek*.
Now רש״י *Rashi* says it's because he cheats people or because he
gives people טריפה *treifa* food because he doesn't want to lose the
פרנסה parnassah? *parnassa*, but obviously the identification with עמלק *Amalek* seems to
more be talking about this bloodlust type of a thing, that it's
a redirected desire for bloodshed. Of course what's bad? He's redirecting it,
so it's not a bad thing. רבי נהוראי *Rabbi Nehorai* אומר *omeir*
מניח אני כל אומנות שבעולם maniach ani kol umanut sheba'olam ואיני מלמד
את בני אלא תורה ve'eini melamed et bni ela Torah *maniach ani
kol umanut sheba'olam ve-eini melameid et bni ela Torah*. I would abandon
all of the
professions and I'm only teaching my son תורה Torah, *Torah*. So the
question, does he mean don't learn a profession, right? Is he disagreeing
that you should just trust it's going to fall from heaven? The
מהרש״א *Maharsha* says no, no, no. What he means is he's reinforcing
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. Learn an easy profession, but don't spend even
too much time in terms of educating the profession. You'll get some
profession. All the emphasis, the focus, should be on preparing your son
for a life of תורה *Torah*. Okay, which doesn't mean you sit
in כולל *kollel*, you obviously get some profession, but you really have
to focus on תורה *Torah* education. שאדם אוכל משכרה בעולם הזה והקרן
קיימת לו לעולם הבא *she-adam ochel mis-chara ba'olam ha-zeh ve-hakaren kayemet lo
l'olam ha-ba*. Okay, because that you'll get the reward in עולם הבא
*Olam Ha-Ba*. ושאר כל אומנות אינו כן *v'sha'ar kol umanut eino kein*.
The other professions aren't this way. כשאדם בא לידי חולי או לידי
זקנה או לידי ייסורים ואינו יכול לעסוק במלאכתו *keshe-adam ba lidei choli
o lidei zikna o lidei yisurim ve-eino yachol la'asok bim-lachto*. A person
has illness or whatever, old age, and he can't do his job.
הרי הוא מת ברעב *harei hu meit ba-ra'av*. Then they'll stop getting
a פרנסה parnassah *parnassa* and he could die from famine. אבל התורה
אינה כן *aval ha-Torah einah kein*. But תורה *Torah* will always pay
your rewards. אלא משמרתו מכל רע בנערותו *ela mishmarto mikol ra b'na'aruto*.
It protects you in your youth. Presumably also the thing it's protecting
in your youth might be sexual temptation. ונותנת לו אחרית ותקווה בזקנותו
*ve-notenet lo acharit v'tikva b'ziknuto*. And also gives you hope in your
old age. בנערותו מה הוא אומר *b'na'aruto ma hu omeir* וקווי השם
יחליפו כוח *v'kovei Hashem yachalifu koach*. Nope, it's וקווי *v'kovei*, וקווי השם
יחליפו כוח *v'kovei Hashem yachalifu koach*. יעלו אבר כנשרים *ya'alu eiver kanesharim*.
I understand, you can go look at that. It's וקווי *v'kovei*. Anyway,
בזקנותו מה הוא אומר beziknuto ma hu omer? *b'ziknuto ma hu omeir*
עוד ינובון בשיבה *od yenuvun b'seivah*. So those that believe in God
will have strength. And in the elder it says, עוד ינובון בשיבה
*od yenuvun b'seivah*, they will be sort of flowering, you know, lush
in their old age. וכן הוא אומר באברהם אבינו *v'chein hu omeir
b'Avraham Avinu* ואברהם זקן בא בימים והשם ברך את אברהם בכל *v'Avraham
zaken ba bayamim v'Hashem berach et Avraham bakol*. מצינו שעשה אברהם אבינו
את כל התורה כולה עד שלא ניתנה *matzinu she'asa Avraham Avinu et
kol ha-Torah kula ad shelo nitna*. He did the whole תורה *Torah*
before it was given. שנאמר shenemar *shenemar* עקב אשר שמע אברהם בקולי
וישמור משמרתי מצוותי חוקותי ותורותי *eikev asher shama Avraham b'koli vayishmor mishmarti
mitzvotai chukotai v'torotai*. Now, why is that in? That seems to be
a complete gloss at the end, right? It's what does him keeping
the תורה *Torah* have to do with the fact about like learning
תורה *Torah* makes you successful in your old age? And by the
way, not only is that a gloss, some scholars say that this
entire משנה mishna *mishna* is a gloss. That basically the real פרק
perek *perek* ended with כל שעסקו עם נשים לא יתייחד עם הנשים
*kol she'asko im nashim lo yityached im hanashim*. Okay, and maybe the
לא ילמד אדם את בנו אומנות הנשים *lo yilameid adam et bno
umanut hanashim*, period. And like from רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* on, it
was all like some later type of a ברייתא braita, *braita* or
a gloss on it, this whole אגדתא *aggadta* thing. So I know
it's already 8:30, but let's just go to the end. I do
want to say one thing though, I'm asking myself, other than the
fact that it's a nice אגדתא *aggadta*... aggadic ending, what the heck
is this doing in מסכת קידושין, Maseches Kiddushin. right? Right? What does
it have to do with קידושין, Kiddushin, what does it have to
do with ייחוד, with anything? And I answer, struck me that maybe
we've been wrong in thinking about that קידושין Kiddushin is just about
marriage. Because if you think about how much the first פרק perek
was about, was also about, right, the parent's obligations to the children.
קידושין Kiddushin starts with the concept of a father marrying off his
daughter, that's the paradigm of קידושין. Kiddushin. קידושין Kiddushin had a lot
to do with acquisition, right, all the קניינים, kinyanim, right, then what
is a parent's obligations to the son? To marry him off, to
teach him תורה, and to teach him a trade. So in a
certain way, right, this פרק and a lot of this about, you
know, parents and children, parents and children were an ongoing theme whether
ייחוס yichus or a father being a שליח shaliach for his son
or whatever the cases might be. So I think more of big
picture, this is about parents preparing their children for lives or generally
like organizing your life. Who are you married to? What is your
פרנסה? parnasa What are like the things that you own? Right? It's
sort of like, so if you look at it, pull back and
look at it through that lens, right, so this is a very
sort of powerful ending here, which it's talking about like, okay, we've
talked about getting married, like what's the type of פרנסה parnasa you
should get? And how does that balance? Those are your three obligations,
right? לישא אשה, Lissa isha, ללמוד תורה, lilmod Torah, you know, ללמדו
אומנות. lamedo umnis. How do you sort of balance the ללמוד תורה
lilmod Torah and ללמדו אומנות lamedo umnis type of a reality? So
I think that really helps explain what this whole end משנה is
doing at the end of מסכת קידושין. masechet Kiddushin All right, let's
just go for a few more minutes. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our
rabbis taught. כל שעסקיו עם הנשים סורו רע. Kol she'asakav im hanashim
su'o ra.
Anybody that's primary job is with women, turning to that person is
a bad news, okay? Stay away from that person. כגון הצורפים, Kigon
hatzorfim, like the people that like smelt and make jewelry, והסריקים, vehasrikim,
and the people that, what does רש"י Rashi say, make, right, like,
right, like make garments or weavers or whatever or embroiderers,
והניקורות, vehanikurot, the people that clean out hand-mills that women would have
like, you know, in terms of their kitchen appliances, והרוכלים, veharochalim, and
people that sell fragrances to women, והגרדיים, vehagardiyim, and tailors, והספרים, vehasaparim,
and barbers, cause the mothers are always bringing their kids to the
barber,
והכובסים, vehakovasin, and launderers, cause all of these are the, so there
you go, Dov, these are all the storekeepers that women are regularly
frequenting. So here it's in that list, okay? והגרע והבלן, Vehagarav vehabalan,
הגרע hagrav is a bloodletter. Okay, so I don't know why that
specifically is with, is an issue about women, and הבלן habalan is
the, is the, what do you call it, the bathhouse attendant, והבורסקי,
vehaburski, and the tanner.
אין
מעמידין מהם לא מלך ולא כהן, Ein ma'amidin mehem lo melech velo
kohen, and among these, some of these people, not you also do
not make them into kings or high priests because these are considered
to be like, like, you know, like inappropriate, low-class types of labors,
and maybe specifically because some of them are smelly or cause they're
manual labor, but also maybe because they have to deal with interacting
with women, which from a male-oriented patriarchal society was seen as more
of a low-class type of a thing.
מאי טעמא לא לא משום דפסלי, Mai ta'ama lo, lo mishum depaslei,
not because they're technically invalid, like we think that these people are
not kosher witnesses or sinners or something of that nature, אלא משום
דזילו אומנותיהו, ela mishum dezilu umnasaihu, because it's a lowly type of
a profession, which a little begs the question. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu
rabanan, עשרה דברים נאמרו בגרע, asarah devarim nemru begarav, ten things were
said about a bloodletter. מהלך על צידו, Mehalach al tzido, so it's,
goes on its side, which might mean like he walks with a
sort of an erect posture, very prideful, ורוחו גסה, verucho gassa, so
he's prideful, וניקלט ויושב, veniklat veyoshev, when he sits, he's always like
reclining and leaning back and stretching out, again showing his like a
little bit his, you know, his גאוה. ga'ava.
ועינו צרה, Ve'eino tzara, he has a, you know,
he's very stingy. רש"י Rashi says he's stingy because he's used to
everybody always treating him. He goes to somebody's house to let blood
and the person after you let blood, you know, they have you
eat some food, so apparently they would have a nice meal afterwards,
so he's always very used to wherever he goes, everybody's comping him,
professional courtesy or whatever, so he never likes to put his hand
in his own pocket, all right? ועינו רעה, Ve'eino ra'ah, and also
he's, he's, he's, he has an evil eye against people. He doesn't
like seeing healthy people around because that means less business for him,
okay? אוכל הרבה ומוציא קימעא, Ochel harbeh umotzi kima, he eats a
lot because he's always being treated to people's
meals, okay, and he defecates only very little. רש"י Rashi says cause
he eats all this good food like good fatty meat and white
bread, so you don't, you don't poop so much with that. I
don't know, anyway. All right, okay. וחשוד על העריות. Vechashud al ha'arayot.
Now this is very interesting. He's suspect of sexual sin. Why? רש"י
Rashi says מתוך שהנשים צריכות לו ועסקיו עמהן. mito shehanashim tzrichot lo
ve'asakav imahem.
So this is very interesting, right, somebody that's got, you know, it's
sort of like the concern about the rabbi that's always, you know,
counseling these women. So women go to him for, you know, people
in positions of power taking advantage is basically what it is. Okay.
ועל הגזל ve'al hagezel cause he robs, you know, he overcharges. על
שפיכות דמים al shefichut damim when he is not careful with his
profession. תניא רבי נהוראי. Tanya Rabbi Nehorai. לעולם ילמד אדם את בנו
אומנות נקיה וקלה. le'olam yelamed adam et bno umanut nkiya vekala. מה
היא? ma hi? What's a clean and easy job? אמר רב יהודה
Amar Rav Yehuda מחטא דתלמיותא. machta detalyuta. A some type of a
like of a of a stitching, okay, or quilt making or something
that, you know, you don't have to make a lot of expenses,
you don't invest a lot of money, you sit and you sit
alone and you just sew. It's easy, it's not it's not laborious
and so on. Okay. Again, I don't know how many people that
do that are
tailors make a fortune and say like the whole statement about Rabbi
Meir, it's all in God's hands. You know, some you're giving God
a more of an opportunity than others. Okay.
תניא, Tanya, רבי אומר, Rebbe omer, אין לך אומנות שעוברת מן העולם.
ein lecha umanut she'overet min ha'olam. You know, there's the world is
always going to need people of different professions. So any job you
have, there's going to be someone who needs that job. אשרי מי
שרואה את הוריו באומנות מעולה, ashrei mi she'roeh et horav be'umanut me'ula,
אוי לו למי שרואה את הוריו באומנות פגומה. oy lo lemi she'roeh
et horav be'umanut pguma. Somebody's got to get the bad jobs, it
doesn't have to be you. So praised are you if you grew
up with parents that had a appropriate job. Now what does Rebbe
mean by appropriate job? Does he mean the same thing as Rabbi
Meir? I mean Rebbe was quite wealthy, he was the נשיא, nasi,
does he mean being a tailor is an אומנות מעולה? umanut me'ula?
Does he have a different sense of what that means? I don't
know exactly. But anyway, Rebbe is saying is it would be good
if it was modeled for you, you know, somebody who grows up
with parents that are professionals and doctors and lawyers, that often sets
them on that type of a path, right? So somebody's gotta have
those other jobs, but you should be trained and brought up inside
that you have the nice jobs. Okay. אוי לו למי שרואה את
הוריו oy lo lemi she'roeh et horav okay. אי אפשר לעולם בלא
בסם ובלא בורסקי. iy efshar la'olam belo basam uvelo borski. The Torah,
the world cannot exist without a perfumer and a tanner. אשרי מי
שאומנותו בסם, ashrei mi she'umanuto basam,
praised is the person who winds up being a perfumer, אוי לו
למי שאומנותו בורסקי, oy lo lemi she'umanuto borski, woe to the person
who winds up being a tanner. אי אפשר לעולם בלא זכרים ובלא
נקבות. iy efshar la'olam belo zacharim uvelo nekevot. What a wonderful way
to end a מסכת. masechet. The world cannot exist without males and
females. אשרי מי שבניו זכרים, ashrei mi shebanav zacharim, אוי לו למי
שבניו נקבות. oy lo lemi shebanav nekevot. Praised is the man who
has boy children, woe to the person who has female daughters
because presumably it's more I mean I imagine it has more to
do with the fact that you have a dowry, you have to
marry them off, they're not considered to be people that are going
to go and earn a living, you know like the whole like
Tevye and his daughters, right? He has five daughters, like the concern
is like he has to provide their dowry and who's going to
be providing for him? So I think in that type of a
world, I hope I would rather read it that way than read
it as this whole extreme sort of like negative statement about what
it means to be a woman.
רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer לעולם ילמד אדם לבנו אומנות נקיה
וקלה le'olam yelamed adam livno umanut nkiya vekala ויבקש רחמים למי שהעושר
והנכסים שלו, veyvakesh rachamim lemi she'haosher vehanechasim shelo, שאין עניות מן האומנות
ואין עשירות מן האומנות she'ein aniyut min ha'umanut ve'ein ashirut min ha'umanut
אלא למי שהעושר שלו ela lemi she'haosher shelo שנאמר לי הכסף ולי
הזהב נאם השם צבאות. li hakesef veli hazahav neum Hashem Tzevaot. So
that's pretty much a restatement of what we had in the Mishna.
Pick a job, make it an easy job, pray to God. Let's
just finish up. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer, if you ever seen an animal getting dressed up in a
business suit? I guess he didn't read The Far Side too much.
תניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer
מימי לא ראיתי צבי קייץ. miyami lo raiti tzvi kayatz. You know,
I never seen a deer who was like a who was a
what do you call it, a drier of figs or whatever that
is. וארי סבל, ve'ari sabal, I never saw a lion that was
a schlepper, that was like a mover. ושועל חנוני veshual chanvani or
a fox that was a storekeeper. והם מתפרנסים בלא צער, vehem mitparnesim
belo tza'ar, they
somehow seem to be taken care of their needs. והם לא נבראו
אלא לשמשני, vehem lo nivreu ela leshamshani, they were created for me.
ואני נבראתי לשמש את קוני. ve'ani nivrati leshamesh et koni. מה אלו
שלא נבראו אלא לשמשני מתפרנסים בלא צער, ma elu shelo nivreu ela
leshamshani mitparnesim belo tza'ar, they get they provide for their needs without
effort. ואני שנבראתי לשמש את קוני אינו דין שאתפרנס בלא צער? ve'ani
shenivrati leshamesh et koni eino din she'etparnes belo tza'ar? אלא שהרעתי את
מעשי, ela she'hareti et ma'asai, my deeds were I made them bad,
וקיפחתי את פרנסתי vekipachti et parnasati and I, you know, I ruined
my my sustenance שנאמר עונותיכם הטו, shenemar avonotechem hitu, it's your sins.
By the way, the other thing I wonder about about the... Yeah,
that's why people assumed that the end of the Mishna was really
might have been a ברייתא, it wasn't really the Mishna, okay? Yes,
it's almost word for word the Mishna, a few a little a
little different. One also wonders whether harkening back to גן עדן Gan
Eden is also also harkening back to the marriage of גן עדן,
Gan Eden, right? כי גן עדן מקדם. ki Gan Eden mikedem. The
whole sense of the קידושין kiddushin there. I haven't sort of unpacked
that, but you know, in מסכת קידושין and talking about like פרנסה
and whatever and גן עדן, Gan Eden, one wonders like where does
marriage fit into that image? Is marriage a thing that wasn't ruined
and the פרנסה was ruined? I don't exactly have to think about
that, right? But we do harken back to that perfect marriage of
גן עדן. Gan Eden. רבי נהוראי אומר Rabbi Nehorai omer מניח אני
כל אומנות. maniach ani kol umanut. תניא רבי נהוראי אומר Tanya Rabbi
Nehorai omer מניח אני כל אומנות שבעולם ואיני מלמד את בני אלא
תורה שכל אומנות שבעולם אינה עומדת לו אלא בימי ילדותו. shekol umanut
sheba'olam eina omedet lo ela bimei yalduto. But בימי זקנותו, bimei ziknuto,
הרי הוא מוטל ברעב. harei hu mutal bara'av. You're going to starve.
Other things. אבל תורה אינה כן, aval Torah eina chen, עומדת לו
לאדם בעת ילדותו omedet lo la'adam be'et yalduto ונותנת לו אחרית ותקוה
בעת זקנותו. venotenet lo acharit vetikva be'et ziknuto. בעת ילדותו מה הוא
אומר? be'et yalduto ma hu omer? וקווי השם יחליפו כח יעלו אבר
כנשרים. vekovei Hashem yachalifu koach ya'alu ever kanesharim. בזקנותו מה הוא אומר?
עוד ינובון בשיבה דשנים ורעננים יהיו. od yenuvun besiva dshanim vera'ananim yihiyu.
הדרן. Hadran. הדרן עלך עשרה יוחסין וסליקא לה מסכת קידושין. Hadran alach
asarah yuchasin uslikla masechet kiddushin. All right,
so we don't have a מנין, minyan, do we? All right, so
we'll wait to do the formal סיום siyum when we have a
סיום siyum whenever that's going to be. יישר כח Yasher koach to
everybody, I will see you tomorrow for בבא קמא. Bava Kamma.